Guide to the Billionaires for Bush Records TAM.725
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Billionaires for Bush Records
2000-2013
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Billionaires (Organization)
TAM.725
11 linear feet in 4 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, 1 half manuscript box, 2 oversize boxes, 1 media box, 1 oversized rolled storage, and 1 flat-file folder
8 videocassettes (vhs)
18 videocassettes (minidv)
23 videodiscs (dvd)
18 sound discs (cd)
8.12 Gigabytes
Billionaires for Bush was a grassroots media campaign that used culture jamming and street theater to satirize politicians supporting corporate interests and the upper class. Activists wore costumes to parody the wealthy and jokingly supported political campaigns, with the greatest amount of activity during the 2000 and 2004 U.S. presidential elections. Since 2005, the group continues to advocate on a number of economic issues, including income inequality, gentrification, taxation policies, and Social Security privatization. The Billionaires for Bush Records document the organization's activism, with majority of the materials in this collection document the group's street theater and other actions during the 2000 and 2004 United States presidential elections. Materials in this collection include photographs, correspondence between organizers, printed suggestions for participating, flyers for distribution at actions, drafts of public statements, promotional ephemera like brochures, notes from planning meetings, newspaper clippings, costumes used in actions, and video recordings of demonstrations or interviews. In addition to documenting specific activism during the 2000 and 2004 presidential elections, the collection reveals a larger context of activism against economic inequality, as well as the tactics used by the organization, such as culture jamming and street theater.
Biographical / Historical
Billionaires for Bush was a grassroots media campaign that used culture jamming and street theater to satirize politicians supporting corporate interests and the upper class. The organization was first founded by Andrew Boyd as "Billionaires for Forbes" during the Republican Party nomination process of the 2000 U.S. presidential election. Activists wore costumes to parody the wealthy and jokingly supported conservative political campaigns benefiting corporate interests, with the greatest amount of activity during the 2000 and 2004 U.S. presidential elections. Since 2005, the group continues to advocate on a number of economic issues, including income inequality, gentrification, taxation policies, and Social Security privatization.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in the order in which it were received from the donor. These materials have been grouped into five series by subject and format as follows:
I. Billionaires for Bush (or Gore)
II. Billionaires for Bush
III. Actions
IV. Performance-Related Materials
V. Audiovisual Materials
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction, with the exception of materials containing sensitive personal or financial information housed in Box 3 that is restricted to researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Andrew Boyd in July 2017; the accession number assocaited with this gift is 2017.044.
Scope and Contents
The Billionaires for Bush Records document the organization's activism during the early 2000s critiquing politicians supporting policies that disproportionately benefitted corporations and the upper-class. The majority of the materials in this collection document the group's street theater and other actions during the 2000 and 2004 United States presidential elections. Materials in this collection include photographs (both print and digital), correspondence between organizers, printed suggestions for participating, flyers for distribution at actions, drafts of public statements, promotional ephemera like brochures or stickers, notes from planning meetings, newspaper clippings, and video recordings of demonstrations and interviews. These materials document many of the group's targeted actions, such as "Block the Vote" that satirized voter suppression tactics, the "Get on the Limo" campaign tour, and "Cheney is Innocent." The collection also includes costumes and accessories worn or used by activists during actions, including banners, tuxedos, buttons, a fur stole, a top hat, plastic cigars, and cufflinks. In addition to documenting specific activism during the 2000 and 2004 presidential elections, the collection reveals a larger context of activism against economic inequality, as well as the tactics used by the organization, such as culture jamming and street theater.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Culture jamming; Street theater.; Political satire, American.; Elections -- United States.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 2004.; Political culture -- United States; Political activists -- United States.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 2000.; Bush, George W. (George Walker), 1946-; Gore, Al, 1948-; Republican National Committee (U.S.); Boyd, Andrew, 1962-
- Series I: Billionaires for Bush (or Gore), circa 2000
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of materials created, collected, or used by Billionaires for Bush activists during the 2000 U.S. presidential election.
  - Background, circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Boyd, Andrew, circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Do-it-Yourself Action and Performance Kit, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General Info, Talking Points, Chants, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Newsclippings, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Other Groups, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Billionaires for Bush, 2000-2013
  This series consists of materials created, collected, or used by Billionaires for Bush activists during the 2004 U.S. presidential election.
  - Articles and Content Background, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Be a Billionaire!": Official Billionaires for Bush Do-it-Yourself Manual, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Book-First Cover Mockup, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Book -- Organizational Ideas and Sketches, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Boyd, Andrew -- Phil T. Rich Media Pack, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Boyd, Andrew -- Phil T. Rich -- Speeches, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Budgets, Receipts, Bling, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Campaign and Organizational Strategy, 2004-2005, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cartoons, Images Mockup, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chants and Slogans, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Character and Comedy Creation, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Digital Photographs, 1995-2004 (E-records TW_TAM_725_1, E-records TW_TAM_725_2, Box TW_TAM_725_3, Box TW_TAM_725_4, E-records TW_TAM_725_5, E-records TW_TAM_725_6)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted.
  - Email Correspondence, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Executive Cabinet Agendas and Cabinet Structure, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Events Calendars, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Finances, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Fundraising Correspondence, Budgets, and Planning, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Haugeraid, Angelique -- "Invitations, Innovations, Ideas"; "Leave No Billionaire Behind" and Political Disertations; Performance Parody, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Interviews-- Nerve, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Kulkharni, Kavita -- "Postmodern Parody as Political Intervention: A Case Study of Billionaires for Bush", 2004 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Media Hits List" Media Coverage, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Media Kits, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Messaging Talking Points, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Newsclippings, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Newsclippings, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Newsclippings, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Newsclippings, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Newsclippings, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Newsclippings, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Newsclippings, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Newsclippings: Clyde Haberman, New York Times, 2004-2009 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Newsclippings (Full Magazines): Time (July 31, 2000), New York (May 17, 2004), Time Out NY (2004), New York (2004), 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Newsclippings (Full Magazines): Time (July 31, 2000), New York (May 17, 2004), Time Out NY (2004), New York (2004), 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Notes -- Handwritten, unknown author, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Notes -- Meetings, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Opprecht, Kurt -- Book Readings, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Opprecht, Kurt -- "How to Rule the World for Fun and Profit," Brainstorming, Press Releases, Notes, and CD, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Opprecht, Kurt -- Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Opprecht, Kurt -- Radio Scripts, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Opprecht, Kurt (Thurston Howell VI) Publications: "The Billionaires Manifesto" and "How to Rule the World for Fun and Profit", 2004, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Other Groups Information Pamphlets and Programs, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Patel, Ricken -- "Faithful Majority" Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Press Releases, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Point People Lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Project Teams, Independent Action Teams and Special Ops, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Post-November 2004 Election Planning (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Poster Ideas and Pricing, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Resumes (Restricted), 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    This folder is restricted to researchers.
  - Royalties and Publishing, 2004, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Sign-Up Lists (Restricted), undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Series III: Actions, 2000-2005
  This series consists of materials created, collected, or used by Billionaires for Bush activists during the 2000 and 2004 U.S. presidential election for the organization's specific actions targeting particular policies, politicians, or large issues. The materials in this series document the organization's strategies to engage the media, as well as the tactics and methods activists used to join existing events led by the politicians they were critiquing, interact with activists pursuing similar goals through different measures, and initiate their own events that encouraged distributed action with individual engagement.
  - Speakers Bureau Documents, undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Billionaire Messaging Dos and Dont's, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Suggestions for Solvency, Recruitment, and Impact, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Actions, Various, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Varon, Jeremy, "Strategery" Meeting Opening Remarks and Summary Transcribed by Angelique Hayward, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Website Design Statement of Work, Correspondence, Notes, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - "Block to Vote" Action and Playing Cards -- Background, Messaging, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Bloomberg Third Term Endorsement by Christine Quinn Action, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Campaign Kickoff/Loft Patry Preparation, Lists, Phil T. Rich, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cheney Gate, "Cheney is Innocent," National Day of Action, Talking Points, Background and Notes, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - CISPAS (Committee in Solidarity with the People of El Savador) and Sweat Gear -- Anti-Sweatshop Campaign -- "Sweat Gear: A Rotating and Blend of Old and New Designs Alter from Old-Fashioned Sweatshops in El Salvador", undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Democratic National Convention Information, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Drink on Powerball -- Calendar and Raffle, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Drink on Poweball -- VIP Planning Correspondence, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Education is not For Everyone" Day -- Messaging and Email, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Florida -- "Don't Vote" Hip-Hop Tour Final Budget, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Get on the Limo" National Summer Swing State Tour Final Budget, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Get on the Limo" Southwest Limo Tour Final Budgets and Receipt, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Get on the Limo" Southwest Tour Planning, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Karl Rove is Innocent Action Fundraising Event, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Drunk on Power -- Budget Art Aution Winners (Restricted), 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Maine Chapter -- Billionaries for Unlimited Inheritance and Battle of Billionaires" Draft Statement and Script, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Nationwide Convergence -- Washington, DC, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Philadelphia Action with Greene Dragon Script, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Republican National Convention Planning, Press Releases Coordination, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Republican National Convention (NYC) -- Publications -- "Alternates Guides to NYC Politics, Culture, and Events,", 2004 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Republican National Convention (NYC) -- Publications About NY (The Independent, The Nation, Z Magazine), 2004 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Spring Bling! Billionaire War Bacchanal Script, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Support Our Troops -- Bring them Home Now Yellow Ribbon Campaign Pitch -- Correspondence, Design, Notes, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Tax Day Press Release and Talking Points, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - United for a Fair Economy -- Fair Taxes for all Campaign -- Messaging, Background, Working Papers, Stickers, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - United for a Fair Economy -- Publications -- Activist Cookbook: Creative Action for a Fair Economy, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - United for a Fair Economy -- Laughing Stock! a Humor Sourcebook for Economic Fairness, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Series IV: Performance-Related Materials
  This series consists of objects created or used by Billionaires for Bush activists for the purposes of demonstrations or other actions, including ephemera for distribution as well as costumes and accessories used to parody the upper-class.
  - Billionaires Follies -- Playbills, Postcards, Christmas Cards, Songbook, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Billionaires Texas Tea Party -- Script (Draft), 2005 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Billionaires in the House Video Filming Receipts, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Billionaires in the House Video Performers, Logo, Photographs, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Billionaires the Musical -- First Draft and Correspondence, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Billionaires the Musical -- Scripts, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Bugdet and Recipts -- Audio, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Informerical Scipts and Concepts, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - "Leave No Billionaire Behind" -- Bush in 30 Seconds -- Moveon.org Finalist Certificates, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "Our Vision Our Future" -- Screenplay for an Informerical for Billionaires for Bush, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Performer Releases -- Billionaires in the House video, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Performer Releases -- Children's Video, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Television,Radio, Video Backgroudn and Planning, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Bookmark -- Billionaires for Bush the Musical: Leave no Billionaire Behind, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Bumper Stickers, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Business Cards, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Buttons, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Flyers, Other Organizations, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Greeting Cards, Billionaires for Bush Photo Cards, and "Drunk on Power" Guest Photo Card, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Map -- "People's Guide to the Republican National Convention", undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Nametags, Assorted from Balls, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Photographs -- Phil T. Rich and Unknown NYC Action, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Photographs -- Philadelphia Action with Green Dragon, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Photographs -- Unknown Bilionaire and Unknown New York City Action, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Placards, Small, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Playing Cards: "Regime Change," "Bush Cards", undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Postcards and Flyers -- Balls and Parties -- Billionaires Ball, Drunk on Power Ball, Re-Coronation Ball, Spring Bling, April Fool's Ball, Karl Rove in NYC, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Postcards and Flyers -- Billionaires for Bush, General, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Postcards -- Republican National Convention -- "Billionaires for Bush Guide to the Convention" and "At the RNC", 2004 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Postcards and Stickers -- Lobbyists for McCain, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Stickers and Tattoos, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Postcards, small -- "We Know a Good Thing When We Buy it" Series, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Trading Cards -- Psychadelic Republicans, undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Calendar, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Top Hat, undated (Box 4)
  - Demonstration Banners, undated (Box 4, Roll-storage 8)
  - Costume Accessories, undated (Box 5)
  - Tuxedo and Fur Stole Costumes, undated (Box 6)
  - Demonstration Placards and Posters, undated (Box 7, Flat-file 1, Drawer 3, Folder 1)
- Series V. Audiovisual Materials
  Arrangement
  Individual items in this series were numbered prior to their transfer to the archives and remain in this order.
  This series consists of audiovisual materials created or collected by members of Billionaires for Bush, including video recordings of demonstration and scripted promotional pieces; sound recordings of songs parodying the wealthy and commercial compilation cds distributed by the organization. This series also includes a small number of VHS tapes about culture jamming and street theater tactics.
  - Video Recordings, 1995-2004 (Box 9, Box 10)
  - Sound Recordings, 1995-2004 (Box 10)